### SHOLA OJO, CPA

Cell Phone: 216.894.5897; Email: <a href="mailto:sholao13@gmail.com">sholao13@gmail.com</a>; Linkedin Profile: <a href="www.linkedin.com/in/shola-ojo">www.linkedin.com/in/shola-ojo</a> 9432 Lakeshore Blvd., Bratenahl, OH, 44108

## SENIOR LEVEL FINANCIAL ANALYST/ACCOUNTANT

Diligent financial/accounting analyst with eight years of experience in the financial field. Proven track record of financial understanding in the areas of budgeting, accounting, internal control, systems application and database management. Excellent verbal and written communication skills with high, mid and low-level personnel. Successful project manager and team leader for projects managed in various career roles.

#### AREAS OF EXPERTISE

- Financial Management
- Financial Reporting
- Financial Accounting
- Internal Control
- Business Process improvement
- Information systems and implementation

- Strategic Business Planning
- Governmental Accounting and Reporting
- Non-Profit Accounting and Reporting
- Project manager
- Bank reconciliation

- Budget implementation and management
- Database management
- Data analysis
- Public Speaking
- Supervisory skills
- Internal and External Customer Service

## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

The Links Foundation Incorporated, Washington, D.C.

## **Senior Accountant** (2017 to Present)

Hired to manage all financial operations and accounting function of the Finance office. Supervise and maintain daily financial operations (cash receipts, cash disbursement, investment transactions, bank reconciliations, fixed asset accounts, payroll and accrual activities) of the Foundation. Financial liaison between the National office and Links Incorporated chapters, and manager of all chapter funds deposited with the Foundation. Conduct the financial audit of the Foundation in conjunction with the National Treasurer. Prepare all Foundation financial reports for the National Treasurer for all board meetings and financial inquiries. Other key duties includes:

- Managing the accounts payable process and maintaining vendor relationships.
- Monitoring grants received and reporting grant requirements as stipulated by grant agreement.
- Work with the Development office to issue tax acknowledgement and tax letters for donations over \$250.
- Maintaining the investment schedule to analyze investment portfolio transactions and monthly recording
  of all portfolio transactions related to the acquisition and sale of bonds, stock and other equity
  instruments, changes in unrealized gains/losses and realized gains/losses. Report investment portfolio
  values to Executive board members of the organization.
- Updating the Foundation's financial manual as needed and communicating Foundation policies to chapter treasurers, members of the Links Foundation and current and prospective donors.
- Documenting Finance procedures and accounting processes to maintain good internal control using the COSO framework.
- Manage all credit card and echeck sales received through payment processing online center. Validate
  sales transaction are successful. Contact customers for failed transactions and process refunds to
  customer after investigating payment issues.

City of Cleveland, Cleveland, OH

Fiscal Manager (2016 to 2017)

Promoted to assist in various City financial projects. Financial projects highlights included:

- Project team member to manage \$50 million grant award from the Department of Justice for the 2016
   Republican National Convention. Role included:
  - o Documenting the internal control process to manage the grant.

Shola Ojo Page 1 of 3

- Coordinating with Safety Department to develop budget for various expenditure related to procurement and personnel needs.
- Meet with internal and external stalk holders to develop process to track safety personnel work hours and developing supporting documentation to track hours.
- o Meet with DOJ auditors to discuss audit guidelines, timeline and audit plan.
- o Manage and organize all audit documentation.
- o Calculate payroll expense for reimbursement.
- Project lead to implement budget software for the Department of Public Utilities. Role included:
  - o Meet and discus with internal stalk holders on software compatibility with current business process and implement business processes with budget software.
  - o Develop end users training material.
  - o Perform software functionality test to ensure system performance functions as intended.

## The City of Cleveland, Cleveland, OH

## **Deputy Budget Administrator (2015-2016)**

Promoted to manage the City's yearly budget development in excess of \$1.6 billion. Project manage various financial report analysis for the Finance Director. Manage day to day budget office operations delegated by the Budget Administrator and act as primary back up to the Budget Administrator. Role highlights included:

- Preparing payroll and benefit data analysis for Finance Director used in arbitration cases for labor negotiations.
- Performing debt analysis to provide sinking fund projections for major capital project improvements to City facilities.
- Managing the City's self-insurance program in conjunction with the City's Assistant Finance Director by
  providing financial analysis, reviewing weekly claims and projecting cash flow needs for funds solvency.
  Meet regularly with healthcare consultants to discuss and implement strategies to decrease employees'
  health insurance expenses, projecting cash flow needs to pay claims, creating employee health plan
  packages, and studying actuarial projections for health services provided but not paid (IBNR).
- Project manage upgrading the City's budget software system. Maintained and updated all data tables in budget software, trained end users and documented procedures for yearly citywide budget input and projection analysis.
- Interviewing and recommending new hires to Budget Administrator and Finance Director. Training new budget staff members on office policies and procedures.

## City of Cleveland, Cleveland, OH

## **Budget Analyst – (2011-2015)**

Promoted to oversee that annually appropriated budget for the Department of Public Safety. Budget liaison between the Finance Office and Department of Public Safety. Prepare monthly revenue and expense projection analysis, with variance explanations reported to Finance Director and Public Safety divisions. Completed assigned projects as directed by Budget Administrator and Finance Director. Role highlights included:

- Analyzing overtime trends expenditure within the Department of Public Safety and providing bi-weekly report on overtime cost driver within the department.
- Updating data tables in the budget software system to perform yearly budget input from City divisions and perform budget projections
- Created headcount excel template utilized by the budget office to report to Finance Director on citywide vacancies and personnel retention in all City divisions.
- Performing what if scenarios projection options on various mechanism to fund the construction of the 3<sup>rd</sup> district police station.

### City of Cleveland, Cleveland, OH

## **Accounting Intern – (2010-2011)**

Initially hired in the Division of Water accounts payable section to research and record vendor invoices in the City's Financial ERP system. Assigned to perform customer billing account reconciliations for the Division of Water. Also interned for the City's Internal Audit division performing assigned audit duties. Major internship highlights included:

Shola Ojo Page 2 of 3

- Performing physical inventory counts in various city facilities.
- Auditing vendor contracts for compliance with City regulations as established by the Office of Equal opportunity.
- Reconciling back log customer water bills accurately and timely.

## Jimmy Burns CPA, Cleveland, OH

# **Accounting Intern – (2009-2010)**

Hired to perform bookkeeping functions for clients. Prepared financial reports for clients and performed bank reconciliations.

East Cleveland Board of Education, East Cleveland, OH

### Permanent Substitute Teacher (2006-2009)

Initially hired as a substitute teacher. Promoted to permanent substitute teacher. Main role was to teach students in the subject area of Physical and Earth Science. Provided lesson activities for students, tracked students progress on lesson assignments and prepared students for yearly State of Ohio graduation exam.

### COMPUTER RELATED SKILLS

- Microsoft Suite (Windows, Excel, Access, Word, Outlook, PowerPoint)
- ➤ CGI Advantage Financial and Performance Budget
- Quick Books
- > Peachtree accounting Software
- > SAP Business Objects
- ➤ Abila MIP Fund Accounting
- > ADP

## PERSONAL QUALITIES

- Quick leaner
- > Organized, fast, and efficient
- > Team player
- > Punctual
- > Responsible
- > Excellent verbal and written communication skills

## **EDUCATION AND CERTIFICATE**

Certified Public Accountant, State of Ohio	2016 - 2020
Member International Institute of Business Analysis	2018 - 2019
Cleveland State University, Master in Accounting	2008 - 2011
University of Cincinnati, Bachelors in Political Science	2002 - 2006
Entry Certificate in Business Analysis	Applicant

## REFERENCES AVAILABLE UPON REQUEST

Shola Ojo Page 3 of 3